<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The profit of imprisonment A paradox, vvritten in French by Odet de la Noue, Lord of Teligni, being prisoner in the castle of Tournay. Translated by Iosuah Silvester.</title>
            <title>Paradoxe que les adversitez sont plus necessaires que les prosperités. English</title>
            <author>La Noue, Odet de, seigneur de Téligny, d. 1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1594</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05075</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15216</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109328</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844978</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844978</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9838</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05075)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9838)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 346:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The profit of imprisonment A paradox, vvritten in French by Odet de la Noue, Lord of Teligni, being prisoner in the castle of Tournay. Translated by Iosuah Silvester.</title>
                  <title>Paradoxe que les adversitez sont plus necessaires que les prosperités. English</title>
                  <author>La Noue, Odet de, seigneur de Téligny, d. 1618.</author>
                  <author>Sylvester, Josuah, 1563-1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Peter Short, for Edward Blunt,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1594.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Paradoxe que les adversitez sont plus necessaires que les prosperités.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴ E² .</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A paradox. against libertie.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Imprisonment --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Korey Jackson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Korey Jackson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9838:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9838:1"/>
            <p>The Profit of <hi>Impriſonment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A PARADOX,</hi> VVritten in French by <hi>Odet de la Noue,</hi> Lord of <hi>Teligni,</hi> being priſoner in the Caſtle of <hi>Tournay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated by IOSVAH SILVESTER.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <q>ET VSQVE AD NVBES VERITAS TVA</q>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London by Peter Short, for Edward Blunt. 1594.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9838:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9838:2"/>
            <head>To the worſhipful his approued <hi>frend maiſter Robert Nicolſon</hi> marchant, Ioſuah Silueſter wiſheth euer all true content.</head>
            <l>TO you, youth's Loadſtar, London's ornament,</l>
            <l>Frend to the Muſes, and the well-inclinde,</l>
            <l>Louing, and lou'd of euery vertuous mind:</l>
            <l>To you theſe tuneles accents I preſent,</l>
            <l>Of humble stile, and vncouth argument,</l>
            <l>Not to requight, but to record your kind</l>
            <l>And gentle fauours, by the which you bind,</l>
            <l>My beſt endeuours to acknowledgment.</l>
            <l>Accept (I pray) this preſent in good part,</l>
            <l>This ſimple pleadge of my ſincere affection,</l>
            <l>Waigh not the worth, but waigh my willing hart</l>
            <l>(Perfect good-will ſuplies all imperfection)</l>
            <l>So may I one day wright your worthy name,</l>
            <l>In better tunes vpon a bigger frame.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:9838:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:9838:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:9838:4"/>
            <head>A Sonnet of the author <hi>to his booke</hi>
            </head>
            <l>THe bodie euer-pròne to pleaſures and delights</l>
            <l>Of ſoft, frayle, daintie fleſh, and to ſelfe-eaſe adicted,</l>
            <l>Abhorrs impriſonment as a baſe paine inflicted</l>
            <l>To puniſh the defaults of moſt vnhappie wights.</l>
            <l>The ſoule as much ſurpriſde with loue of heauenly ſights</l>
            <l>And longing to behold the place that appertains her</l>
            <l>Doth loath the bodie, as a priſon that detaine her</l>
            <l>From her high happines among the bleſſed ſprights</l>
            <l>Then, ſith both bodie and ſoule their bondage neur brooke</l>
            <l>But ſoule and bodie both do loue their libertie:</l>
            <l>Tell, tell me (o my muſe) who will beleeue our booke?</l>
            <l>He that hath learnd aright both theſe to mortefie,</l>
            <l>And ſerue our ſauior Chriſt in body and in ſpirite</l>
            <l>Who both from thrall hath freed by his owne only merit.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:9838:4"/>
            <head>A Paradox <hi>That aduerſitie is more neceſſarie then pro</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie: and that of all afflictions, cloſe priſon is moſt pleaſant and moſt profitable.</head>
            <byline>By the Lord of Teligni.</byline>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow euer fondlie-falſe a uaine opinion bee,</l>
               <l>If the vile vulgar once approue it, commonly</l>
               <l>Moſt men eſteeme it true: ſo great a credit brings</l>
               <l>Conſent of multitude, euen in abſurdeſt things.</l>
               <l>Nor any meane remains when it is once receiued,</l>
               <l>To wreſt it from the moſt of erring minds deceiued.</l>
               <l>Nay, who ſo ſhall but ſaie, they ought to alter it,</l>
               <l>Hee headlong caſts himſelfe in daungers deepeſt pit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For neuer nimble barke that on aduenture runns</l>
               <l>Through thoſe blewe bounding hills where horie <hi>Neptun</hi> wunns</l>
               <l>Was ſet vpon ſo ſore with neuer-ceaſt aſſault</l>
               <l>Maintaind on euery ſide by winds and waters ſalt,</l>
               <l>When raging moſt they raiſe their rougheſt tempeſt dreaded</l>
               <l>As th'idiot multitude, that monſter many-headed</l>
               <l>Beſtirrs it ſelfe with wrath, ſpight, furie, full of terror</l>
               <l>Gainſt what ſoeuer man that dares reproue her error.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who vndertakes that taske, muſt make account at firſt</l>
               <l>To take hote warrs in hand and beare awaie the worſt.</l>
               <l>Therfore a many workes, worthy the light, haue died</l>
               <l>Before their birth, in breſts of fathers terrified</l>
               <l>Not by rough deeds alone; but euen by fooliſh threats:</l>
               <l>"Yet onlie noiſe of words baſe cowards onlie beats.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then feare who liſt for mee the common peoples crie,</l>
               <l>And who ſo liſt be mute, if other minded: I</l>
               <l>(Skorning the feeble force of ſuch a vaine endeuour)</l>
               <l>Will freely, ſpight of feare; ſay what I cenſure euer:</l>
               <l>And though my preſent ſtate permit mee not ſuch ſcope,</l>
               <l>Mine vnforbiden pen with error's pride ſhall cope.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:5"/>Cloſe priſon now adaies th'extreameſt miſerie</l>
               <l>The world doth deeme, I deeme direct the contrarie:</l>
               <l>And therwithall will proue that euen aduerſities</l>
               <l>Are to bee wiſhed more then moſt proſperities:</l>
               <l>And for impriſonment though that bee moſt lamented,</l>
               <l>Of all the greefs wherewith men feare to be tormented,</l>
               <l>Yet that's the ſtate moſt ſtoar'd with pleaſure and delight,</l>
               <l>And the moſt gainfull too to any chriſtian wight.</l>
               <l>A <hi>Paradox</hi> no doubt more trew, then creditable,</l>
               <l>The which my ſelfe ſometimes haue alſo thought a fable,</l>
               <l>While guilfull vanities, fed not, but fild my mind,</l>
               <l>For ſtrengthning ſuſtenance, with vnſubſtanciall wind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I hated death to death, I alſo did deteſt</l>
               <l>All ſicknes and diſeaſe that might a man moleſt.</l>
               <l>But moſt I did abhorre that baſe-eſteemed ſtate,</l>
               <l>Which to ſubiections law our ſelues doth ſubiugate,</l>
               <l>And our ſweet life enthralls vnto an others will,</l>
               <l>For as my fancie wiſht I would haue walked ſtill.</l>
               <l>Death (thought I) ſoone hath don, &amp; euerie greefe beſides,</l>
               <l>The more extreme it is the leſſer time abides:</l>
               <l>But now, beſides that I eſteemd the priſoners trouble</l>
               <l>Much worſe, mee thought the tyme his martirdome did dubble.</l>
               <l>So that to ſcape that skourge ſo irkſome to my hart,</l>
               <l>I could haue bin content to ſuffer any ſmart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lo by blind ignorance how iudgments are miſſ-led:</l>
               <l>Now that full thirtie months I haue, experienced,</l>
               <l>That ſo much-feared ill, 'tis now ſo vſd to mee</l>
               <l>That I a priſoner liue much more content and free,</l>
               <l>Then when as vnder cloake of a falſe freedome vaine,</l>
               <l>I was baſe ſlaue indeede to many a bitter paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now I ſee my ſelfe mockt euery where almoſt</l>
               <l>And feeble mee alone met by a mightie hoaſt</l>
               <l>Of ſuch as, as in this caſe do not conceaue as I,</l>
               <l>But do eſteeme them ſelues offended much thereby.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And therfore (father deere) this weake abortiue child,</l>
               <l>For refuge runnes betwene th'armes of his granſire mild,</l>
               <l>If you accept of it, my labour hath his hire,</l>
               <l>For careles of the reſt all that I heere deſire,</l>
               <l>Is only that your ſelfe as in a glaſſe may ſee</l>
               <l>The image of th'eſtate of my captiuitie,</l>
               <l>Where, though I nothing can auaile the common weale,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:5"/>Yet I auaile my ſelfe at leaſt ſome little deale.</l>
               <l>Praiſing th'all powerfull Lord, that thus vouchſafes to poure,</l>
               <l>Such fauours manifold vpon mee euery houre;</l>
               <l>Wherof your ſelfe yer while ſo ſweete ſure proofe haue taſted,</l>
               <l>In cruell bitternes of bands that longer laſted,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now I beſech his grace to bleſſe mine enterpriſe,</l>
               <l>My hart and hand at once to gouerne in ſuch wiſe,</l>
               <l>That what, I wright, may nought diſpleaſing him containe:</l>
               <l>For voide of his ſweet aide who works he works in vaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Within the wide-ſpred ſpace of theſe round Elements,</l>
               <l>What ſoeuer is indewd with liuing ſoule and ſence,</l>
               <l>Seeks of it ſelfe ſelfe-good; this inſtinct naturall</l>
               <l>Nature her ſelfe hath grauen in harts of creatures all,</l>
               <l>And of all liuing things from largeſt to the leaſt</l>
               <l>Each one to flie his ill doth euermore his beſt.</l>
               <l>Thereof it comes (we ſee) the wilde horſe full of ſtrength,</l>
               <l>Tamelie to take the bit into his mouth at length,</l>
               <l>And ſo by force we tame each moſt vntamed beaſt,</l>
               <l>Which of it ſelfe, diſcreet, of evils takes the leaſt:</l>
               <l>And though that, that which ſeems to be his chiefe reſtraint</l>
               <l>He often times deſpiſe, that's by a worſe conſtraint,</l>
               <l>As when the Lyon fierce, fearleſſe purſues the ſhining</l>
               <l>Of bright keen-pearcing blades, and's royall creſt declining</l>
               <l>Full of the valiant fyre, that courage woonts to lend,</l>
               <l>Runs midſt a million ſwords his whelplings to defend,</l>
               <l>More fearing farre that they their libertie ſhould loſe,</l>
               <l>Than on himſelfe the ſmart of thouſand wounding blowes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But all things haue not now the ſelfe ſame goods and ils,</l>
               <l>What helpeth one, the ſame another hurts and kils:</l>
               <l>There's ods betweene the good that ſauage beaſts do like,</l>
               <l>And that good (good indeed) which ſoul-wiſe man muſt ſeek:</l>
               <l>When beaſts haue ſtore of food, and free from foe's annoy,</l>
               <l>Smart-leſſe, and ſound, and ſafe, may as they liſt enjoy</l>
               <l>Their fill of thoſe delights, that moſt delight the ſence:</l>
               <l>That, that's the happineſſe that fullie them contents.</l>
               <l>But reaſonable ſoules (as God hath made mankind)</l>
               <l>Can with ſo wretched good not ſatisfie their mind.</l>
               <l>But by how much the more their inlie ſight excels</l>
               <l>The brutiſh appetite of everie creature els,</l>
               <l>So much more excellent the good for which they thirſt,</l>
               <l>Man of two parts is made, the body is the wurſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:6"/>The heav'n-borne ſoule, the beſt, wherein mans bliſſe abides,</l>
               <l>In bodie that of beaſts, nought having els beſides:</l>
               <l>This bodie ſtands in need of many an acceſſorie,</l>
               <l>To make it ſomewhat ſeeme: the ſoule reciues this glorie</l>
               <l>That ſelfelie ſhe ſubſiſts; and her aboundant wealth.</l>
               <l>(Vnlike the bodies ſtore) is ever ſafe from ſtealth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our bodie tooke his birth of this terreſtriall clod.</l>
               <l>Our ſpirit, it was inſpir'd of th'inlie breath of God;</l>
               <l>And either of them ſtill ſtrives to his proper place,</l>
               <l>This earth-born, ſtoopes to earth; that ſties to heauen apace.</l>
               <l>But as the ſillie bird, whoſe wings are wrapt in lime,</l>
               <l>Faine, but in vaine, attempts to flie full many a time:</l>
               <l>So our faire ſoule ſurcharg'de with this foule robe of mudd,</l>
               <l>Is too-too often held from mounting to her GOOD.</l>
               <l>She ſtriues, ſhe ſtrikes, ſomtimes ſhe lifts her vp aloft,</l>
               <l>But, as the worſer part (we ſee) preualeth oft,</l>
               <l>This falſe fraile fleſh of ours with pleaſure's painted lure,</l>
               <l>Straight makes her ſtoop again downe to the duſt impure,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Happie who th'honour hath of ſuch a victorie,</l>
               <l>He crownes his conquering head with more true maieſtie</l>
               <l>Then if he had ſubdued thoſe nations, by his might,</l>
               <l>Which do diſcouer firſt <hi>Aurora's</hi> early light,</l>
               <l>And thoſe whom <hi>Phaebus</hi> ſees from his <hi>Meridian</hi> mount,</l>
               <l>Th' <hi>Anti-podes,</hi> and all; more then the ſand to count.</l>
               <l>For ſmall the honor is to bee acknowledgd King</l>
               <l>And monarke of the world, ones ſelfe vn-maiſtering.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But each man on his head this garland cannot ſet,</l>
               <l>Nor is it giuen to all this victorie to get,</l>
               <l>Only a verie few, gods deere belou'd elect</l>
               <l>This happie goale haue got by vertew's lyue effect,</l>
               <l>The reſt, ſoone werie of this ſame ſo painfull warr,</l>
               <l>Like well of heauen, but loue the earth before it farr:</l>
               <l>Some, druncke with poiſonie dreggs of worldly pleaſures brute,</l>
               <l>Know where true good conſiſts, bur neuer do enſew't:</l>
               <l>Some, do enſue the ſame, but with ſo faint a hart,</l>
               <l>That at the firſt aſſalt they do retire and ſtart;</l>
               <l>Some, more couragious, vow more then they bring to paſſe</l>
               <l>(So much more eaſie 'tis to ſay, then do, alas)</l>
               <l>And al through too much loue of this vain worlds alureme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</l>
               <l>or too much idle feare of ſufferings and endurements:</l>
               <l>Meere vanities, whereto, the more men do incline</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:6"/>The farther of they are from their cheefe good deuine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Therefore, ſo manie thinke themſelues ſo miſerable,</l>
               <l>Therfore the aire is fild with out-cries lamentable,</l>
               <l>Of ſuch as do diſdaigne the thing that better is,</l>
               <l>To entertaine the worſe, with forfeit of their bliſſe,</l>
               <l>Therefore, we ſee thoſe men that riches do poſſeſſe,</l>
               <l>Afflicted ſtill with care, and therefore, heauineſſe</l>
               <l>Abandons neuer thoſe, that, fed with honnor's fill,</l>
               <l>Fawne vp-on Potentats, for flitting fauour ſtill;</l>
               <l>And cauſe (God wot) they haue, to be at quiet neuer</l>
               <l>Sith their felicitie is ſo vncertaine euer.</l>
               <l>Neither are Kings them ſelues exempted from vexacion</l>
               <l>How-euer ſoueraigne ſway they beare in any nation,</l>
               <l>For now they wiſh to win, anon feare loſſe no leſſe,</l>
               <l>Yea though for empire they did this wide world poſſeſſe,</l>
               <l>Not one of them, with all, could full contented bee,</l>
               <l>For how man more attaines, the more attempteth hee.</l>
               <l>Who (therfore) couets moſt ſuch ſoon-paſt goods vncertain</l>
               <l>Shall n'er enioye the ioye of goods abiding-certain,</l>
               <l>But who ſo ſeekes to build a true content to laſt,</l>
               <l>On elſe-what muſt elſe-where his firſt foundacion caſt,</l>
               <l>For all things here below are apt to alter euer;</l>
               <l>Heer's nothing permanent, and therfore who ſoeuer</l>
               <l>Truſts therto, truſteth to a broken ſtaffe for ſtay;</l>
               <l>For no earths vanitie can bleſſe a man for aye.</l>
               <l>We muſt, to make vs bleſt, our firme aſſurance found</l>
               <l>Els where then in this world, this chaunge-inthraled ground</l>
               <l>We muſt propoſe our ſelues that perfect, perriſh-les,</l>
               <l>That true vnfained good, that good all danger-les</l>
               <l>From th'uniuſt ſpoile of theeues, which neuer, neuer ſtands</l>
               <l>In need of guard, to guard from ſoldiors pilling hands.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now tis with ſpirituall hands and not with corporall</l>
               <l>That we do apprehend theſe heauenly treaſures all</l>
               <l>Treaſures ſo precious, that th'only hope to haue-them</l>
               <l>In full fruition once, with him that frankly gaue-them,</l>
               <l>Fills vs with euery ioy, our ſorrows choakes and kills,</l>
               <l>And makes vs feele, amid our moſt tormenting ills,</l>
               <l>A much more calme content, then thoſe that euery day</l>
               <l>On this fraile earth enioy their harts wiſh euery way</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It's therfore in the ſpirite not in the fleſh that we</l>
               <l>Muſt ſeeke our ſoueraigne good and cheife felicitie</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:7"/>Th'one is not capable of any iniurie,</l>
               <l>Th'other's thrall to the yoake of many a miſerie</l>
               <l>Th'one endles, euer laſts, th'other endures ſo little</l>
               <l>That wellnigh yer't be got tis gone it is ſo brittle.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For who is he that now in wealth aboundeth moſt,</l>
               <l>Or he that in the Court Kings fauours beſt may boaſt,</l>
               <l>Or he that's moſt with robes of dignitie bedight,</l>
               <l>Or he that ſwimmes on ſeas of ſenſuall ſweet delight,</l>
               <l>But is in perrill ſtill to proue the contrarie,</l>
               <l>Poore, hated, honnor-les and full of miſerie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But one, that skorning all theſe rich proud pomps &amp; pleaſures</l>
               <l>About him euer bears like <hi>Bias</hi> all his treaſures,</l>
               <l>Euen like to him can leaue his natiue countrie ſackt,</l>
               <l>Without ſuſtaine of loſſe: and with a mind infract,</l>
               <l>Euen vanquiſhed bereaue the victors victories,</l>
               <l>Who, though his land he win, cannot his hart ſurpriſe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let exile, priſonment, and tortures great and ſmall,</l>
               <l>With their extreameſt paines at-once aſſaile him all,</l>
               <l>Let him be left alone among his mightie foes,</l>
               <l>Poore; frendles, naked, ſicke, (or if ought worſe then thoſe)</l>
               <l>He doth not onely beare all this with patience,</l>
               <l>But taketh euen delight in, ſuch experience:</l>
               <l>Regarding all theſe greefs, which men ſo much affright,</l>
               <l>As babie-fearing buggs, and skar-crowes void of might:</l>
               <l>He chuſeth rather much ſuch excercize as theſe,</l>
               <l>Then mid the fleſh delights to ruſt in idle eaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But verie fewe ther are that thus much will admit,</l>
               <l>Nay few or non there are that eaſely credit it;</l>
               <l>The moſt part taking-part with common-moſt conceat.</l>
               <l>Yer they haue heard of this, ſuſtain the tother ſtreight:</l>
               <l>Not ſeeing that themſelues ſhunne and refuſe as ill</l>
               <l>What vnto other men for good they offer ſtill</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not one of them will brooke his ſonne in ſloath to lurke</l>
               <l>But moues, and ſtirrs him vp inceſſantly to worke:</l>
               <l>Forbids him nothing more then ſin-ſeed idlenes:</l>
               <l>Nor any pleaſure vaine permitts him to poſſeſſe,</l>
               <l>(For well he knowes, that way to vertue doth not lead,</l>
               <l>But the therward who walkes a path of paine muſt tread)</l>
               <l>If he offend in ought he chaſtens and reproues him,</l>
               <l>In ſomuch ſharper ſort by how much more he loues-him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus handleth man the thing that moſt he holdeth deere</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:7"/>Yet thinks it ſtrange himſelfe ſhould ſo be handled heer.</l>
               <l>May we not rather thinke we are belou'd of God,</l>
               <l>When as we feele the ſtripes of his iuſt-gentle rod?</l>
               <l>And that, whom heere he letts liue as they liſt in pleaſure,</l>
               <l>Are ſuch as leaſt he loues, and holds not as his treaſure?</l>
               <l>For ſo, not of our ſlaues, but of our ſonnes elect,</l>
               <l>By ſharp-ſweet chaſtiſements the manners we correct.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In verie deed God doth as doth a prudent Sire</l>
               <l>Who little careth what may croſſe his childs deſire</l>
               <l>But what may moſt auaile vnto his betterment</l>
               <l>So knowing well that eaſe would make vs negligent,</l>
               <l>He excerciſeth vs, he ſtirres vs vp and preſſes,</l>
               <l>And though we murmur much, yet neuer more he ceaſes,</l>
               <l>He chaſtens, he afflicts; and thoſe whom moſt he ſtriketh</l>
               <l>Are thoſe whom moſt he loues, and whom he chiefly liketh.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No valiant men of war will murmur or miſlike</l>
               <l>For being plac'd to proue the formoſt puſh of of pike,</l>
               <l>Nay rather would they there alreddy frunt the foe,</l>
               <l>With loſſe of deareſt blood their dauntleſſe harts to ſhow.</l>
               <l>If an exploit aproach, or battle-day drawnie,</l>
               <l>If ambuſh muſt bee laid, ſome ſtratagem to trie;</l>
               <l>Or muſt they meet the foe in eger skirmiſh fell,</l>
               <l>Or for the ſleepie hoaſt all night keepe ſentinell:</l>
               <l>From grudging at the paines, ſo farr of are they all,</l>
               <l>That bleſt they coumpt themſelues; therefore their Generall</l>
               <l>Imployes them often times, as moſt couragious;</l>
               <l>And them approud, he plants in places dangerous,</l>
               <l>But no man makes account of ſuch as ſhun the charge,</l>
               <l>Whoſe paine is not ſo little as their ſhame is large,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All of vs in this world reſemble ſoldiors right,</l>
               <l>From daie breake of our birthe euen to our dying night,</l>
               <l>This life it is a war, wherein the valianteſt,</l>
               <l>With hotteſt skirmiſhes are euer plied and preſt:</l>
               <l>Whom our grand Captain moſt ſetts-by he ſetts a-frunt,</l>
               <l>The fore-ward, as moſt fit to beare the cheefeſt brunt:</l>
               <l>Cares, exiles, priſonments, diſeaſes, dollours, loſſes,</l>
               <l>Maimes, tortures, torments, ſpoiles, contempts, diſhonors, croſſes</l>
               <l>Al theſe are hard exploits, &amp; ful of bickerings bold,</l>
               <l>Which he commits to thoſe whom he doth deereſt hold.</l>
               <l>But leaueth thoſe behind for whom he careth little,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:8"/>To ſtretch the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues at eaſe amid their honors brittle</l>
               <l>Their pomps, their dignities, their ioies, their gems, their treſurs</l>
               <l>Their dainties, their delights, their paſtims, &amp; their pleaſurs</l>
               <l>Like coward groomes that guard the baggage &amp; the ſtuffe</l>
               <l>While others meet the foe &amp; ſhow their valours proofe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But haue not theſe (ſay ſome) in theſe afflictions part?</l>
               <l>No; but of puniſhment, they often feele the ſmart.</l>
               <l>Afflicted thoſe we count, whom chaſtnings tame, and turne,</l>
               <l>The other puniſhed, that at correction ſpurne.</l>
               <l>The firſt ſtill full of hope, reape profit by their rods,</l>
               <l>The later deſperate, through ſpight wax wurſe by ods.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Boy-ſtragglers of a camp, ſo ſhould be puniſht then</l>
               <l>Beeing naked forc't to fight with troupes of armed men,</l>
               <l>Who cannot reap nor reach the pleaſure, nor the meed</l>
               <l>Nor th'honour incident for doing ſuch a deed,</l>
               <l>To ſuch praiſe-winning place, braue ſoldiors gladly run,</l>
               <l>Which as a dangerous place theſe faint-harts ſadly ſhun.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What warriour in the world, that had not rather trie</l>
               <l>A million of extremes, yea rather euen to die,</l>
               <l>Then with diſgracefull ſpot to ſtaine his honnor bright</l>
               <l>In theſe corporeall warrs? Yet in the ghoſtly fight</l>
               <l>Of glorie careles all, we ſhunn all labours paine,</l>
               <l>To purchaſe with reproch a reſt-neſt idely-vaine:</l>
               <l>Vertue is not atchiu'd, by ſpending of the yeere</l>
               <l>In pleaſures ſoft, ſweet ſhades, downe beds and daintie chere,</l>
               <l>Continuall trauell'tis that makes vs there ariue</l>
               <l>And ſo by trauell too vertue is kept a liue;</l>
               <l>For ſoone all vertue vades without ſome excerciſe</l>
               <l>But being ſtird, the more her vigour multiplies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Beſides, what man is he, that feeles ſome member rotten</l>
               <l>Whereof hee fears to die, but cauſeth ſtraight be gotten,</l>
               <l>Some Surgeon that with ſaw, with cauter, or with knife,</l>
               <l>May take that part awaie to ſaue his threatned life:</l>
               <l>And ſuffers (though with ſmart) his very fleſh and bones</l>
               <l>To be both ſeard, and ſawd, and cleane cut-of at-once.</l>
               <l>But to recure the ſoule: the ſoule with ſinne infected,</l>
               <l>All wholeſome remedies are hated and reiected.</l>
               <l>With the Phiſition kind th'impatient patient fretts,</l>
               <l>Nor to come neere him once his helpfull hand he letts:</l>
               <l>Wee are halfe putrified, through ſinnes contagious ſpott,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:8"/>And without ſpeedie helpe the reſt muſt wholie rott.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Cut-of th'infected part, then are we ſound and free,</l>
               <l>Els all muſt periſh needs, there is no remedie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Moſt happie they, from whome in this fraile life, the Lord</l>
               <l>(With ſmart of many paines,) cuts-of the paines abhord</l>
               <l>Of th'euer-neuer death, wherein they lye and languiſh,</l>
               <l>That heer haue had their eaſe and neuer taſted anguiſh.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But many, which as yet the aduerſe part approoue,</l>
               <l>Conceaue (if not confeſſe) that it doth more behooue</l>
               <l>By faintles exerciſe faire vertue to maintaine</l>
               <l>Then ouerwhelmd with vice, at reſt to ruſt in vaine.</l>
               <l>But yet the'xtremitie of ſufferings doth diſmay-them,</l>
               <l>The force where of they feare would eaſilie ouer-lay them,</l>
               <l>They loue the exerciſe, the chaſtnings likewiſe like them</l>
               <l>But yet they would haue God but ſeld &amp; ſoftly ſtrike-them</l>
               <l>Els are they preſt to run, to ruine, with the deuills,</l>
               <l>They are ſo ſore affeard of falfe-ſuppoſed euills:</l>
               <l>Moſt wretched is the man that for the feare of nifles,</l>
               <l>All liuely breathing hopes of happie goodnes ſtifles,</l>
               <l>Of nifles, ſir (ſay they) ſeem all their bitter croſſes</l>
               <l>As nothing? nor their paines, nor lamentable loſſes,</l>
               <l>That daily they indure? were not the wretches bleſt</l>
               <l>If from their heauie load their ſhoulders were releaſt?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who is not happie ſure in miſerie and woe,</l>
               <l>No doubt proſperitie can neuer make him ſo,</l>
               <l>No more then he that's ſick ſhould find more eaſe and good</l>
               <l>Vpon a golden bed, then on a bed of wood.</l>
               <l>Man harbors in him ſelfe the euill that afflicts-him,</l>
               <l>And his owne fault it is, if diſcontentment pricks-him:</l>
               <l>And all theſe outward ills are wrongfully accuſed,</l>
               <l>Which fleſh and blood doth blame; for being rightly vſed</l>
               <l>They all turne to our good: but who ſo takes offence</l>
               <l>Thereby, hath by and by his iuſt rough recompence:</l>
               <l>For neither in their power nor in their proofe the ſame,</l>
               <l>Are euills in effect but in conceipt and name.</l>
               <l>Which when we lightlie waigh, the leaſt of vs ſurmounts them</l>
               <l>Nor hurt they any one but him that ouer-counts the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Neither ought that indeed for euill to be rated</l>
               <l>Which may by accident be vnto good tranſlated:</l>
               <l>For ill is euer ill, and is contrarie euer</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:9"/>Directly vnto good, ſo that their natures neuer</l>
               <l>Can be conſtraind to brooke each other, neither yet</l>
               <l>Can thone be euer turnd to th'other oppoſit:</l>
               <l>But plainly we perceaue that thear's no languor ſuch,</l>
               <l>But long continuance and cuſtome lighten much.</l>
               <l>Familiarizing ſo the fit that how ſo frett it</l>
               <l>Euen in th'extremitie one may almoſt forget it</l>
               <l>What better proofe of this, then thoſe poore gallie-ſlaues</l>
               <l>Which (hauing been before ſuch rogues and idle knaues)</l>
               <l>As ſhunning ſeruices to labour wear ſo loth,</l>
               <l>That they would ſtarue and die rather then leaue their ſloth,</l>
               <l>But being vſd a while to tug the painfull oare,</l>
               <l>Labour that earſt they loathd they now deſire the more:</l>
               <l>Or thoſe that are aſſaild with burning feuer-fit</l>
               <l>Euen then when leaſt of all they dread or doubt of it:</l>
               <l>Which carefully complaine, and crie, and raue, and rage,</l>
               <l>Frying in inward flames the which they cannot ſwage;</l>
               <l>Yet if it wax not worſe, the daintieſt bodie makes it</l>
               <l>In eight daies as a vſe, and as a trifle takes it,</l>
               <l>Or thoſe that haue ſometimes the painfull racke indured,</l>
               <l>Who without chainge of paine being a while inured,</l>
               <l>The paine that did conſtraine them to bewaile and weepe,</l>
               <l>Seemes them ſo eaſie then, they almoſt fall a-ſleepe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All are not euils then, that are ſurnamed ſo</l>
               <l>Sith euill neuer can his nature mingle, no</l>
               <l>Nor turne it into good; wheras we plainly ſee</l>
               <l>On th'other ſide, that theſe are changed ſodainly.</l>
               <l>And were they ills indeed, ſith they ſo little laſt</l>
               <l>Wear't not a very ſhame to be ſo much agaſt?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But heer again (ſay they) th'ons nature neuer taketh</l>
               <l>The others nature on, but ſtill the ſtronger maketh</l>
               <l>His fellow giue him place, and onlie beareth ſway</l>
               <l>Till that returne againe, driue it againe away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nay that can neuer be: for neuer perfect good</l>
               <l>Can by his contrarie be banniſht (though withſtood)</l>
               <l>For good is euer good, and where ſo ere it goe</l>
               <l>Euill doth euer ſtriue, but with too ſtrong a ſoe.</l>
               <l>There is no reaſon then, theſe, good, or ill to call,</l>
               <l>That alter in this ſort, and neuer reſt at all:</l>
               <l>Neither to bleſſe or blame them for the good or ill</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:9"/>That euer in her ſelfe our ſoule concealeth ſtill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For if that from without our bale, or els our bliſſe</l>
               <l>Arriued: euer more withall muſt follow this,</l>
               <l>That alwaies, vnto all, ſelfe ill, ſelfe pain, would bring:</l>
               <l>Selfe good, one ſelfe content: but 'tis a certaine thing,</l>
               <l>They are not taken for their qualitie and kind,</l>
               <l>But rather as th'affects of men are moſt inclind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One, looſing but a crowne hath loſt his pacience quight,</l>
               <l>Another hauing loſt fiue hundred in a night,</l>
               <l>Is neuer mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d a iote, though (hauing leſſe in ſtore,</l>
               <l>Then the'other hath by ods) his loſſe might greue him more</l>
               <l>One beeing baniſhed doth nothing but lament,</l>
               <l>Another, as at home, is there as well content.</l>
               <l>And one in priſon pent is vtterlie diſmaide,</l>
               <l>Another, as at home, liues there as well appaid.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Needs muſt we then confeſſe, that in our ſelues doth reſt,</l>
               <l>That which vnhappieth vs, and that which makes vs bleſt:</l>
               <l>In vs indeed the ill, which of our ſelues doth growe:</l>
               <l>And in vs too the good, which from god's grace doth flowe</l>
               <l>To whom it pleaſeth him: true good that none can owe-yet,</l>
               <l>Saue thoſe on whom the Lord vouchſafeth to beſtow-it:</l>
               <l>And that the bitter ſmart of all the paines that wring-vs,</l>
               <l>From nothing but our ſin, receaueth ſtrength to ſting-vs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yea ſurely in our ſelues abides our miſerie,</l>
               <l>Our Grand-ſire <hi>Adam</hi> left vs that for legacie,</l>
               <l>When he enthrald him ſelfe vnto the law of ſin,</l>
               <l>Wherein his guiltie heires their greef-full birth begin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Lord had giuen to him a Nature and a feature</l>
               <l>Perfect indeed and bleſt aboue all other creature;</l>
               <l>And of this Earthlie world had ſtabliſht him as King</l>
               <l>Subiecting to his rule the raines of euerie thing:</l>
               <l>His ſpirit within it ſelfe no ſelfe-debates did nurſe</l>
               <l>Hauing no knowledge yet of better nor of wurſe:</l>
               <l>His bodie euer blith and healthfull felt no war,</l>
               <l>Of thoſe fower qualities that now do euer iar,</l>
               <l>Nor any poyſonie plant nor any ſerpent fell,</l>
               <l>Nor any noyſome beaſt could hurt him any deale:</l>
               <l>He might, without the taſt of bitter death attaine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Vnto the hauen of heauen, where all trew Ioies doe raigne.</l>
               <l>And had he not misdone he might haue well bequeathed,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:10"/>The ſame inheritance to all that euer breathed,</l>
               <l>How happie had he bin, if he had neuer eaten,</l>
               <l>Th'unlawfull fatall frute that double death did threaten,</l>
               <l>O that he neuer had preferd the ſerpent's flatter</l>
               <l>Before th'eternall law of all the world's creator.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You ſhallbe (ſaid the fiend) like ſupreme deities,</l>
               <l>This ſweet frutes ſugred iuice ſhall open both your eyes</l>
               <l>Which now your tirant God enuying all your bliſſe</l>
               <l>Blinds with a filmie vaile of blacke obſcurities,</l>
               <l>Leaſt that you ſhould become his equalls in degree</l>
               <l>Knowing both good and ill as well as euer he.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Poore <hi>Eue</hi> beleues him ſtraight, and Man beleeus his wife</l>
               <l>And biteth by and by the apple asking-life:</l>
               <l>Whereof ſo ſoone as hee had taſted, he beginns</l>
               <l>(But all too-late alas) to ſee his curſed ſinnes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His eyes indeed were ope, and then he had the skill</l>
               <l>To know the difference between the good and ill</l>
               <l>Then did he know how good, good was when he had loſt-it</l>
               <l>And euill too he knew (but ah too deerly coſt-it)</l>
               <l>Leauing himſelfe (beſides the ſorrow of his loſſe)</l>
               <l>Nothing but ſad diſpaire of ſuccor in his croſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He found him ſelfe falne down from bliſſe-full ſtate of peace</l>
               <l>Into a ciuill war where diſcords neuer ceaſe:</l>
               <l>His ſoule reuolting ſoone became his bitter foe</l>
               <l>But (as it oft befalls that worſt do ſtrongeſt grow)</l>
               <l>She is not eaſde at all by th'inly ſtriuing iarres</l>
               <l>Which do annoye her more them th'irefull open warrs.</l>
               <l>Wrath, hatred, enuie, feare, ſorrow diſpare and ſuch:</l>
               <l>And pasſions oppoſite to theſe, afflicte as much,</l>
               <l>Diſtracting to an fro the Princeſſe of his life,</l>
               <l>In reſtles, mutinies and neuer-ceaſing ſtrife.</l>
               <l>Then th'humor-brethren all, hott, cold, and wet, and drie</l>
               <l>Falne out among themſelues, augment his miſerie.</l>
               <l>So that by their debate within his fleſh there ſeeded</l>
               <l>A harueſt of ſuch weeds as neuer can be weeded.</l>
               <l>All creatures that before as ſubiects did atend him</l>
               <l>Now, mong themſelues conſpire by al means to offend-him</l>
               <l>In breefe, Immortall borne, now mortall he became,</l>
               <l>And bound his ſoule to bide hells euer-burning flame,</l>
               <l>Leauing his wofull heires euen from their birth,s begining</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:10"/>Heires of his heavie paine, as of his hainous ſinning.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So that in him the Lord condemned all mankind,</l>
               <l>To beare the puniſhment to his foule ſinne aſsign'd:</l>
               <l>And none had ever ſcap't, had not the God of grace,</l>
               <l>(Deſiring more to ſaue, then to ſubvert his race)</l>
               <l>Redeem'd vs by the death of his deare onely ſonne,</l>
               <l>And choſen vs in him before the world begunne,</l>
               <l>Forgiuing vs the fault, and with the fault, the fine;</l>
               <l>All ſaue this temporall death, of <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne the ſigne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now in the horror of thoſe eaſe-leſſe, end-leſſe paines,</l>
               <l>It may be rightlie ſaid that evill ever raignes:</l>
               <l>That's evill's verie ſelfe, and not this ſeeming-woe,</l>
               <l>Whereof the wanton world complaineth dayly ſo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Liv'd we ten thouſand yeares continuallie tormented</l>
               <l>In all fell tortures ſtraunge that ever were invented,</l>
               <l>What's that compar'd to time, that never ſhall expire,</l>
               <l>Amid th'infernall flames, whoſe leaſt-afflicting fyre</l>
               <l>Exceedeth all the paines, all mortall hearts can think?</l>
               <l>Sure all that we endure, till <hi>Laethe</hi> droppes we drink</l>
               <l>Tis all but eaſe to that, or if it be a paine</l>
               <l>Is in reſpect of that a verie trifle vaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But were't a great deale worſe, why ſhould we evil name,</l>
               <l>That which we rather finde a medicine for the ſame?</l>
               <l>Health, wealth, ſecuritie, honour, and eaſe do make vs</l>
               <l>Forget our God, and God for that doth ſoone forſake vs:</l>
               <l>Whereas afflictions are the readie meanes to mooue vs</l>
               <l>To ſeeke our health in him that doth ſo dearly loue-vs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Tis true indeed (ſay ſome) that benefite they bring-vs,</l>
               <l>But yet the ſmart thereof doth ſo extreamely wring-vs,</l>
               <l>That th'evill which they feele that doe endure the ſame,</l>
               <l>Makes them eſteeme it iuſt to giue it that for name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mans nature, certainly (it cannot be denyed)</l>
               <l>Is thrall to many throwes, while heer on earth we bide</l>
               <l>In bodie and in ſoule: the troubled ſoule ſoſtaines</l>
               <l>A thouſand paſsions ſtrong, the bodie thouſand paines,</l>
               <l>And that's the wretched ſtate, the which yere-while I ſaid,</l>
               <l>Was iuſtlie due to vs, when <hi>Adam</hi> diſobayd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But he that's once new-borne in Ieſus Chriſt by faith,</l>
               <l>Who his aſſured hope in God ſole ſetled hath,</l>
               <l>Who doth beleeue that god giues eſſence vnto all,</l>
               <l>And all ſuſtaineth ſtill, that nothing doth befall</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:11"/>But by his ſacred will, and that no ſtrength that ſtriveth</l>
               <l>To ſtop his iuſt decrees, can ſtand or euer thriueth.</l>
               <l>Not onely doth accept all paines with patience,</l>
               <l>The which he takes for due vnto his deepe offence:</l>
               <l>Nor only is content, if ſuch be gods good pleaſure,</l>
               <l>To feele a thouſand fold a much more ample meaſure,</l>
               <l>But euen delights therein, and void of any feare,</l>
               <l>Expects th'extremitie of all aſſaults to beare.</l>
               <l>Whether almightie god abate their woonted vigor,</l>
               <l>Or (that his may not feele their croſſes cruell rigor)</l>
               <l>Do wholly arme them with new forces for the nonce,</l>
               <l>To beare the bitter brunt: or whether both at-once.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And to approoue this true; how many daylie drink</l>
               <l>Of torments bitter cup, that neuer ſeeme to ſhrink?</l>
               <l>Alas, what ſharper ſmart? what more-afflicting paines?</l>
               <l>What worſer griefe than that, which ceaſ-leſlie ſuſtaines</l>
               <l>He that by ſome miſchaunce, or els by martiall thunder,</l>
               <l>Vnhappily hath had ſome maine bone broke in ſunder?</l>
               <l>What torment feeleth not the ſore-ſicke deep-diſeaſed?</l>
               <l>One while with cruell fit of burning fever ceaſed:</l>
               <l>Another while aſſailde with collicke and with ſtone,</l>
               <l>Or with the cure-leſſe Gout, whoſe rigour yeelds to none.</l>
               <l>Or thouſand other griefes, whoſe bitter-vexing ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Diſturbes continuallie the quiet of our life?</l>
               <l>Yet notwithſtanding this, in all this painfull anguiſh,</l>
               <l>(Though the moſt part repine, &amp; plain, &amp; mourn, &amp; languiſh,</l>
               <l>Murmuring againſt the Lord, with malcontented voice)</l>
               <l>Some praiſe his clemencie, and in his rods reioyce.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How manie ſuch (deare Saints) haue fel tormentors ſeen,</l>
               <l>To die betweene their hands, through moody tyrants teen?</l>
               <l>So little daunted at their martyrdome and ſlaughter,</l>
               <l>That in th'extremitie they haue expreſſed laughter.</l>
               <l>How many at the ſtake, nay, in the verie flame,</l>
               <l>Haue ſung with cheerful voice, th'almighties praiſ-ful name;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet were they all compact of Artirs and of vaines,</l>
               <l>Of ſinewes, bones, and fleſh: and ſenſible of paines,</l>
               <l>(By nature at the leaſt) as much as anie other,</l>
               <l>For being iſſued all from one ſelfe earthly mother,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What makes them then to find ſuch extream ſmart ſo ſweet</l>
               <l>What makes them patientlie thoſe deadly pangs to meet,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:11"/>No doubt it is the Lord, who firſt of nothing made-vs,</l>
               <l>Who with his liberall hand of goodnes ſtill doth lade-vs</l>
               <l>Some more, and other leſſe: and neuer ceaſeth ſpace</l>
               <l>From making vs to feele the fauours of his grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Accurſt are they indeed whom hee doth all abandon</l>
               <l>To doe their luſt for law, and run their life at randon.</l>
               <l>Accurſt who neuer taſt the ſharp-ſweet hand of God;</l>
               <l>Accurſt, ah, moſt accurſte who neuer feele his rod.</l>
               <l>Such men by nature borne the bond-ſlaues vnto ſinne,</l>
               <l>Through ſelfe-corruption end, worſe then they did beginne:</l>
               <l>For how thy longer liue, the more by their amiſſe,</l>
               <l>They draw them neerer hell and farther of from bliſſe.</l>
               <l>Such men within themſelues their euill's ſpring containe</l>
               <l>Their is no outward thing (as falſly they complaine)</l>
               <l>Cauſe of their cureles ill: for good is euerie thing,</l>
               <l>And good can, of it ſelfe, to no-man euill bring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now if they could aright theſe earthly pleaſures prize</l>
               <l>According to their wurth, they would not in ſuch wiſe,</l>
               <l>For lacke, or loſſe of thoſe, ſo vaine and tranſitorie</l>
               <l>Lament ſo bitterlie, nor be ſo ſadlie-ſorrie.</l>
               <l>But ouer-louing ſtill theſe outward things vnſtable,</l>
               <l>To reſt in true content, an howre, they are not able,</l>
               <l>No not a moment's time, their feare doth ſo aſſaile-them,</l>
               <l>And if their feare fall true, that their <hi>Good fortun</hi> faile-them,</l>
               <l>Then ſwell their ſullen harts with ſorrow till they burſt</l>
               <l>And then poore deſperat ſoules they deeme themſelues acc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urſt:</l>
               <l>And ſo indeed they are, but yet they err in this,</l>
               <l>In blaming other things, for their owne ſelfe-amiſſe,</l>
               <l>Other indifferent things, that neither make, nor marre,</l>
               <l>But to the good, bee good; to th'euill, euill are.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Is't not great foliſhnes, for any to complaine,</l>
               <l>That ſomthing is not don, which doth him nought co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrain?</l>
               <l>Sith if he vſe the ſame, ſoule-health it hurteth not,</l>
               <l>Nor if hee doe not vſe't it helpeth not a iot.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But needs muſt we complain, (ſay ſome) for we haue cauſe;</l>
               <l>Then at your perrill bee 't; for that which cheefly drawes</l>
               <l>You therto, tis intruth your brutneſſe in miſdeeming</l>
               <l>Things euill, that are good (for ſence-contrarie ſeeming)</l>
               <l>And whilſt that in the darke of this foule errors miſt,</l>
               <l>Your drowſie ſpirits do droop, alas what maruell iſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:12"/>If euill follow you, and if iniurious ſtill</l>
               <l>To others you impute your ſelfe-ingendered ill?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Happie are they to whom the Lord vouchſafeth ſight</l>
               <l>To ſee the louelie beames and life-infuſing light,</l>
               <l>Of his ſweet ſacred truth; whereby we may perceaue</l>
               <l>And iudge arightly, what to loue, and what to leaue.</l>
               <l>Such men within their ſoules, their goods haue wholy plaſt</l>
               <l>Such goods, as neuer fire can either burne or waſt:</l>
               <l>Nor any theefe can ſteale, nor pirate make his praie,</l>
               <l>Nor vſurie conſume, nor tirant take awaie;</l>
               <l>Nor times all-gnawing tooth can fret awaie, nor finiſh,</l>
               <l>Nor any accident of ſad miſchance deminiſh.</l>
               <l>For it is built on God, a rocke that euer ſtands,</l>
               <l>Not on the vanities of theſe inconſtant ſands</l>
               <l>Which are more mutable then wind and more vnſtable,</l>
               <l>And day by day doe make ſo many miſerable.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O to what ſweet content, to what high ioyes aſpires,</l>
               <l>He that in God alone can limmit his deſires!</l>
               <l>He that in him alone his hopes can wholie reſt,</l>
               <l>He that for only end, waites for the wages bleſt</l>
               <l>Wherewith he promiſeth for euer ſans reſpect</l>
               <l>Of their ſelfe-meriting, to guerdon his elect.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What is it can bereaue the wealth of ſuch a man?</l>
               <l>What is it that diſturb his perfect pleaſures can?</l>
               <l>What is it can ſupplant his honnors and degrees?</l>
               <l>Sith all his treaſures, his delights, his dignities</l>
               <l>Are all laid vp in heauen: where it were all in vaine</l>
               <l>For all the ſonnes of earth to war with might and maine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No doubt (will ſome man ſay) each chriſtian doth aſpire</l>
               <l>After this bodies death to thoſe deer treaſures higher</l>
               <l>That are reſerud in heauen, whereof the ſweet poſſesſion,</l>
               <l>Feares not the violence of all the worlds oppresſion:</l>
               <l>But whileſt that here below this fraile fleſh-burthen ties him,</l>
               <l>But the bare hope he hath, which how can it ſuffice-him</l>
               <l>Againſt the ſharpe aſſalts of pasſions infinite</l>
               <l>Whoſe glad-ſad croſſe conflicts afflict him day and night?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Needs muſt I graunt indeed, that that ſame perfit ioye</l>
               <l>We cannot perfitly vpon this earth enioye:</l>
               <l>But that that hope alone doth not ſufficiently,</l>
               <l>Bleſſe his life where it liues, for my part I denie.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:12"/>Some do not feare we ſee, to ſpend their ſtocke and ſtore,</l>
               <l>To vndertake the taske of manie trauailes ſore:</l>
               <l>To hazard limmes and liues in ſeruice of ſome Lord,</l>
               <l>Depending oft vpon his foole-fat-feeding word:</l>
               <l>Or waiting els perhaps, without all other hold</l>
               <l>Vntill it pleaſe himſelfe his francknes to vnfold,</l>
               <l>Not reaking all their paine they are ſo inly pleaſed,</l>
               <l>With hoped benefite wherof they are not ſeazed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſhall th'aſſured hope of euer-bliſſes then</l>
               <l>For which we haue the word, not of vain mortall men,</l>
               <l>That teach their tongues to lie; but of the higheſt God</l>
               <l>The God of truth, truth's ſelfe, where truth hath ſtil abode:</l>
               <l>Shall that (I ſay) not ſerue to ſettle our faint harts,</l>
               <l>Againſt (I will not ſay) like dangers and like ſmarts:</l>
               <l>But gainſt theſe pettie greefs that now and then do pain-vs</l>
               <l>No more like thoſe then heauen neer earth that doth ſuſtain-vs?</l>
               <l>Ah, ſhall we then diſpiſe all trouble and vexacion,</l>
               <l>Supported by a prop of doubtfull expectation:</l>
               <l>And while for earthly things we can endure this</l>
               <l>Shall we not do aſmuch for an immortall bliſſe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Indeed not of our ſelues, for ſelf-ly nought we can,</l>
               <l>But God when pleaſeth him doth giue this ſtrength to man,</l>
               <l>Whereby he ſtandeth ſtout: euen like a mightie rocke</l>
               <l>Amid the mounting waues when <hi>Eol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> doth vnlock</l>
               <l>Sterne <hi>Austers</hi> ſtormie gate, making the waters wraſtle</l>
               <l>And ruſh with wrathfull rage againſt the ſturdie caſtle</l>
               <l>Whilſt it, for all the force of their fell furie ſhowne</l>
               <l>Is not ſo much as mooud, and much leſſe ouerthrowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So fareth ſuch a man: for if from high degree,</l>
               <l>He ſoudainly do ſlide, to liue contemnedly</l>
               <l>With the vile vulgar ſort, that cannot make him wauer,</l>
               <l>For well he is aſſurd that gods high holie fauour</l>
               <l>Depends not on the pomp, nor vaine, proud ſtate and port,</l>
               <l>That for the grace of kings adorne the courtly ſort.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If he be kept in bands, thrall to the tirannies</l>
               <l>And extreame cruell lawes of ruthles enimies,</l>
               <l>Both voide of helpe and hope, and of all likelihood</l>
               <l>Of beeing euer freed from their hands thirſting-blood;</l>
               <l>In ſpight of them he knowes that one daie he ſhall die,</l>
               <l>And then he ſhall enioy an endles libertie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:9838:13"/>
               <l>If he be forc't to flie from his deare country-clime</l>
               <l>In exile to expire the remnant of his time,</l>
               <l>He doth ſuppoſe the world to be a countrie common,</l>
               <l>From whence no tirranie till death can baniſh no man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If that he muſt forſake his parents and his kin,</l>
               <l>And thoſe whoſe amitie he moſt delighteth in,</l>
               <l>He knowes that where he finds a man, he finds a kinſ-man</l>
               <l>For all mankind is come from one ſelfe father ſinnes-man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If being ſpoild of wealth, and wanton pampering plentie</l>
               <l>He find vpon his boord two diſhes skant of twentie,</l>
               <l>And to his back one coate to keepe the cold awaie</l>
               <l>whereas he had before a new for euerie daie:</l>
               <l>He learneth of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who bidds vs be content,</l>
               <l>With food and furniture to this life competent,</l>
               <l>Sith nothing (as ſaith <hi>Iob</hi>) into this world we brought</l>
               <l>Nor with vs when we die can we hence carrie ought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If he be pasſing poore, and in exceeding lacke</l>
               <l>Of euery needfull thing for belly and for backe,</l>
               <l>He learneth of the Sonne, that God the Father heedeth,</l>
               <l>To giue to euery one, in time, the thing he needeth:</l>
               <l>And that the fowles of heauen, and cattle ſmall and great,</l>
               <l>Doe neither ſowe nor reap, yet find they what to eate:</l>
               <l>Yea that the <hi>Lillies</hi> faire which grow among the graſſe</l>
               <l>Do neither ſpin nor worke and yet their garments paſſe</l>
               <l>For culler and for coſt, for art and ornament,</l>
               <l>The glorious <hi>Salomon's</hi> rich robes of Parlament.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If ſo, that he be ſicke, or wounded in the arme,</l>
               <l>In bodie, backe, or breſt, or ſuch like kind of harme:</l>
               <l>If in extremitie of angrie pain and anguiſh</l>
               <l>Enfeebled ſtill by fitts, he bed-rid lye and languiſh:</l>
               <l>If all the miſeries that euer martird man</l>
               <l>At once on euery ſide afflict him all they can:</l>
               <l>The more that he endures, the more his comforts grow,</l>
               <l>Sith ſo his wretchednes he ſooner commes to know</l>
               <l>That from worlds vanities he may himſelfe aduaunce</l>
               <l>Which hold al thoſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen, that ſtil delight that daunce.</l>
               <l>He feares not thoſe at all that with their vtmoſt might,</l>
               <l>Hauing the bodie ſlaine can do no farther ſpight:</l>
               <l>But only him that with ten thouſand deathes can kill,</l>
               <l>The ſoule and bodie both for euer if he will:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:13"/>He knowes it is their lot that ſeeke to pleaſe their God</l>
               <l>To be afflicted ſtill with perſecutions rod,</l>
               <l>So that what euer croſſe, how euer ſharp aſſaile-him</l>
               <l>His conſtant hart's content and confort cannot faile-him</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But he muſt die (ſay you), alas can that diſmay?</l>
               <l>Where is the labourer that (hauing wrought all day</l>
               <l>Amid the burning heat, with wearines oppreſt)</l>
               <l>Complaines that night is come when he ſhall go to reſt.</l>
               <l>The Marchant that returnes from ſome far forrain lands,</l>
               <l>Eſcaping dreadfull rocks and dangerous ſhelfs and ſands,</l>
               <l>When as he ſees his ſhip her home-hauen enter ſafe,</l>
               <l>Will he repine at God, and as offended chafe</l>
               <l>For being brought to ſoone home to his natiue ſoile,</l>
               <l>Free from all perills ſad that threaten ſaylor's ſpoile?</l>
               <l>He knowes, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thouſand deaths that this one death doth loſe him</l>
               <l>That in heauens euer-ioyes, he euer may repoſe-him:</l>
               <l>That he muſt bring his barke into this creeke, before</l>
               <l>In th'euer laſting land he can ſet foote a-ſhoare:</l>
               <l>That he can neuer come to incorruption,</l>
               <l>Vnles that firſt his fleſh do feele corruption:</l>
               <l>So that all rapt with ioy, hauing his helpe ſo reddie,</l>
               <l>This ſhip-wracke he eſcapes, as on a rocke moſt ſteddie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But more perhaps then death the kind of death diſmaieth,</l>
               <l>Which ſerues him for a bridge that him to heauen co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uaieth.</l>
               <l>Whether he end his daies by naturall diſeaſe:</l>
               <l>Or in a boyſterous ſtorme do periſh on the ſeas:</l>
               <l>Or by the bloodie hands of armed foes be ſlaine:</l>
               <l>Or by miſchaunce a ſtone fall downe, and daſh his braine:</l>
               <l>Or by the murdring ball of new-found earthly thunder</l>
               <l>By day or els by nighr his bones be paſht a-ſunder</l>
               <l>Or burned at a ſtake; or bitterly tormented,</l>
               <l>By cruell ſlaughter-men, in tortures new-inuented.</l>
               <l>Alas, alas, for that, much leſſe then leaſt he careth:</l>
               <l>For as a man falne downe into a pit, he fareth,</l>
               <l>Who if he may be drawne vp from the noiſon place</l>
               <l>Where adders, toades, and ſnakes crawle ouer feet and face,</l>
               <l>Reſpects not, whether that ye vſe a ſilken skaine,</l>
               <l>Hemp-rope, or chaine of gold, ſo he get vp againe:</l>
               <l>Euen ſo, ſo he may come to his deſired bliſſe</l>
               <l>The manner and the meanes to him indifferent is,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:14"/>As for the differing paine (if any him doe torture)</l>
               <l>If it be violent, he knowes it is the ſhorter:</l>
               <l>But be it n'er ſo long, long ſure it cannot laſt</l>
               <l>To vs, whoſe Poſt-like lyfe is all ſo quickly paſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now ſuch a man, in whom ſuch firme contents doe hyue,</l>
               <l>Who can denie to be the happieſt man alyue?</l>
               <l>And who ſo impudent, that dareth now profeſſe,</l>
               <l>That this worlds ſained ſweet (whoſe vnfainde bitterneſſe</l>
               <l>Brings to this verie lyfe full many torments fell,</l>
               <l>And after dingeth downe to th'endles paines of hell.)</l>
               <l>Should be preferd before theſe ſeeming-ſowres, that make vs</l>
               <l>Taſte many true-ſweet ſweets yer this dead lyfe forſake vs.</l>
               <l>And after lift vs vp to that ſame bleſſed ioy,</l>
               <l>That evermore ſhall laſt, exempt from all annoy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So few there will be found (as I ſuppoſe) ſo deeming,</l>
               <l>As manie which (more feard with theſe ils falſly-ſeeming:</l>
               <l>Than inlie falne in loue with heauen-ioyes excellence)</l>
               <l>Approouing this eſtate, flye't as the peſtilence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And yet in this eſtate is found felicity,</l>
               <l>(As farre foorth as it may amid the vanitie</l>
               <l>Of this fraile fading world, where ech thing hourly changes,</l>
               <l>For neuer from it ſelfe true happineſſe eſtranges.</l>
               <l>It neuer doth decay, it neuer doth decreaſe,</l>
               <l>In ſpight of angrie warre it euer liues in peace.</l>
               <l>Maulgre poore want, it hath ten thouſand kinds of wealth,</l>
               <l>Amid infirmities it hath continuall health.</l>
               <l>Invirond round with woe, it doeth reioyce and ſing:</l>
               <l>Depriv'd of dignities, it's greater than a king.</l>
               <l>It ſits ſecure and ſafe, free from hart-pining feares,</l>
               <l>For euer with it ſelfe it all deere treaſures beares.</l>
               <l>Not needing any aide of men of armes to watch-them,</l>
               <l>Nor fearing fraud, nor force of any foe to catch-them.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whereas we daylie ſee ſo many men, whoſe mind</l>
               <l>To tranſitory traſh of world wealth is inclinde,</l>
               <l>In their aboundance beg, and in their plentie poore,</l>
               <l>(For who hath had ſo much, that hath not wiſhed more?)</l>
               <l>No treaſures can ſuffice the gulfe of their deſire,</l>
               <l>Yea, make them Emperours, yet will they more aſpire.</l>
               <l>Peace cannot pacifie the fell rebellious broyle</l>
               <l>That in their troubled ſoule doth euer burne and boyle.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:14"/>For euery ſhort content of any falſe delight,</l>
               <l>A thouſand bitter throwes torment them day and night.</l>
               <l>All their eſtate doth ſtand abroad in hands of ſtrangers,</l>
               <l>Therfore the more their wealth, the more their daily dangers</l>
               <l>The more their miſeries, becauſe the more they need,</l>
               <l>Much ſtrength and many men vnto their hoords to heed:</l>
               <l>Dreading with cauſe, leaſt craft and crueltie, or either,</l>
               <l>Bereaue them of their bliſſe, and treaſure both together.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Needs muſt we then confeſſe that in adverſitie,</l>
               <l>There is more happineſſe then in proſperitie,</l>
               <l>Sith that the mind of man ſo ſoone it ſelfe betrayes,</l>
               <l>Vnto the guilefull ſnares that worldly pleaſure layes,</l>
               <l>Which make vs at the laſt headlong to hell to runne:</l>
               <l>All which adverſitie doth make vs ſafelie ſhunne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But here it may be askt, if pleaſure, ſtate and ſtore,</l>
               <l>(Plunging vs in the pit of vices more and more)</l>
               <l>Be ſubiect ſo to make vs more and more accurſt,</l>
               <l>Muſt we eſteeme that greefe (which ſence eſteemeth wurſt)</l>
               <l>More fit to better vs, and bring vs vnto bliſſe,</l>
               <l>Then thoſe whoſe ſmarting ſting is not ſo ſtrong as this?</l>
               <l>Sure, ſith that in our ſelues our cauſe originall,</l>
               <l>Of bliſſe, and bale we hyde, it matters not at all,</l>
               <l>For ſtill the faithfull man one and the ſame remaines,</l>
               <l>Whether the griefe be great or little he ſuſtaines:</l>
               <l>Sith how ſo ere it be, he takes occaſion thence,</l>
               <l>To ſeeke in God alone, his comfort and defence.</l>
               <l>But for becauſe our ſoule, the while ſhe doth conſort</l>
               <l>With this groſſe fleſhlie lump, cannot, but in ſome ſort</l>
               <l>Suffer as ſenſible, yea, oftentimes ſo far,</l>
               <l>That her beſt functions all, leſſe apt and able are</l>
               <l>Than els at other times: I do ſuppoſe the prooffe</l>
               <l>Of one, then other ill, auailes more in behoofe:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That this is ſo, we ſee, a ſicke man oft to find</l>
               <l>Such ioyfull quietnes, and comfort in his mind,</l>
               <l>That he eſteems himſelfe the beſt content a-liue:</l>
               <l>But yet the ſharpe diſeaſe, which doth his health depriue,</l>
               <l>Withholdeth in ſome ſort his ſences and his wit,</l>
               <l>That freely other-where he cannot vſe them fit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſo it fares with him, that through reſolued wel,</l>
               <l>Endures the cruell ſtraines of any torture fell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:9838:15"/>
               <l>Now for the banniſhd man, the chaunging of his dwelling</l>
               <l>Neuer diſturbes his ioye. And he whoſe wealth excelling</l>
               <l>Turnes in a trice to want, by whatſoeuer chaunce,</l>
               <l>His courage neuer ſhrinks nor yet his countenaunce.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So that in their content, all foure are all a-like,</l>
               <l>A-like reioycing all in their afflictions eeke:</l>
               <l>A-like contemning all world's pompous vanities,</l>
               <l>But the two laſt, haue odds in their extremities</l>
               <l>In that without impeach, they may applie their mind</l>
               <l>To many goodly things, wherin great ioy they find.</l>
               <l>(I meane when each diſtreſſe offends a man alone,</l>
               <l>Not when he is aſſailde at once of euery one.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet perril's quickly paſt, danger endureth not,</l>
               <l>Exile ſo eaſie growes that it is ſoone forgot,</l>
               <l>The greateſt loſſe that is we mind not many hours,</l>
               <l>For thouſand accidents dictract this ſoule of ours,</l>
               <l>Which cannot in ſuch ſort the ſences ſtill reſtraine</l>
               <l>But that they will goe feede on many obiects vaine</l>
               <l>Whereby at vnawares ſhe oftentimes ſurpriſd,</l>
               <l>Is ouer reacht by thoſe, whoſe rigour ſhe diſpiſd:</l>
               <l>And ſo the pleaſant taſt ſhe doth vntimely miſſe,</l>
               <l>Wherewith affliction ſweet doth ſeazon heare her bliſſe,</l>
               <l>So that, ſome other ſtate (wherein our ſoule, leſſe fed</l>
               <l>With ſundrie obiects vaine, ſhalbe more ſettled)</l>
               <l>May rightly be preferd to theſe which make her ſtay,</l>
               <l>And ſtumble often-times, vnto her owne decay,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And therfore I ſuſtaine, cloſe priſon to be beſt,</l>
               <l>Of all afflictions that may a man moleſt.</l>
               <l>Conſidering, all defects to other croſſes common,</l>
               <l>In this are ſeldome found, and almoſt, felt of no man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For Priſon is a place where God ſequeſters men,</l>
               <l>Far from the vile proſpect of vanities terren,</l>
               <l>To make them thence with-draw their harts and to confeſſe,</l>
               <l>That in his grace alone conſiſts their happines.</l>
               <l>It is a learned ſcoole, where God himſelfe reades cleerly</l>
               <l>True wiſedomes perfect rules, to thoſe he loueth deerly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There, th'underſtanding, (free, amid the many chaines,</l>
               <l>That bind the bodie faſt) finds out a thouſand meanes,</l>
               <l>To learne another daie to be more apt and able</l>
               <l>According to our place for vſes ſeruiceable,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:15"/>To proffit publike-weale for euermore we ought,</l>
               <l>In ſeeking ſelfe-gaine ſee that common good be ſought,</l>
               <l>Knowledge is only learnd by long excercitation:</l>
               <l>For which, what fitter meane then ſuch a ſequeſtration,</l>
               <l>Where each-man vndiſturbd, through dilligence may grow</l>
               <l>According to the guifts that gracious heauens beſtowe:</l>
               <l>One in abilitie to rule a lawfull ſtate,</l>
               <l>The vertuous to aduaunce, and vicious to abate:</l>
               <l>Another, from the Tombe to fetch Antiquitie:</l>
               <l>Another to diſcerne true truth from ſophiſtrie,</l>
               <l>Another by the feats of elder men at Armes,</l>
               <l>To fram wiſe ſtratagems for wofull warrs allarmes,</l>
               <l>(For ſouldiars oftentimes may more experience get</l>
               <l>By reading, then they can where camp and camp is met)</l>
               <l>And (breeflie to conclud) ſome, grauely to aduiſe,</l>
               <l>Some, bold to execute, as each mans calling lies:</l>
               <l>But moſt of all, to ſearch within the ſacred writt,</l>
               <l>The ſecret miſteries to mans ſaluation fitt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A world of vanities, that do diſtract vs heer</l>
               <l>During our libertie; in durance, come not neer:</l>
               <l>The wall that letts our leggs from walking out of doore</l>
               <l>Bounding vs round about within a narrow floore,</l>
               <l>Doth gard vs from the gall which Sathan ſpring of ſpight,</l>
               <l>Mingles among the ſweet of this vaine worlds delight.</l>
               <l>If he be happier man that liueth free from foes</l>
               <l>Then he whom angrie troopes of enimies incloſe:</l>
               <l>Much more the priſoner then of his high bliſſe may boaſt</l>
               <l>For being ſo far of from ſuch a hugie hoaſt</l>
               <l>Of hatefull foes ſo fierce in mallice and in might,</l>
               <l>Himſelfe ſo fainte and weake, and ſo vnfit to fight:</l>
               <l>For he, and we God wot in ſteed of ſtanding to-it</l>
               <l>(How-euer in a vain, we vaunt that we will do-it)</l>
               <l>When't commeth to the brunt we cannot brooke the field</l>
               <l>But either flie like hares, or els like cowards yeeld.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſundrie obiects fond, which make vs ſoone forget</l>
               <l>Each other chaſtiſement, in this do neuer let</l>
               <l>For turne we where we liſt and looke which waie we will</l>
               <l>At all times to our ſight one thing is offred ſtill,</l>
               <l>Whether on pauement, roofe, or wall we caſt our eye,</l>
               <l>Alwaies of our eſtate an Image we diſcrie,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:16"/>And ſo it alſo fares with our newes-greedie eare,</l>
               <l>One very ſound reſounds about vs euery where:</l>
               <l>Where euer harken we, we heere of nought but foes,</l>
               <l>Our keepers commonlie are not too kind (God knowes)</l>
               <l>By the leaſt noiſe that is continually they tell</l>
               <l>In what eſtate we ſtand and in what houſe we dwell.</l>
               <l>So that inceſſantlie our harts are lift on high:</l>
               <l>Some times to praiſe the lord for his benignitie,</l>
               <l>Who doth not puniſh vs after our foule offence,</l>
               <l>Though by a thouſand ſinnes we daily him incenſe:</l>
               <l>Some times to magnifie his admirable might</l>
               <l>Which hath our feeble harts with ſuch great force bedight</l>
               <l>That we, in ſteed of greef, or grudging at the paines,</l>
               <l>Of ſharpeſt chaſtiſements, whereof the world complaines,</l>
               <l>Leauing this loathed Earth we mount the higheſt place</l>
               <l>Where through true faith we taſt his hunnie-ſweeter grace:</l>
               <l>Some times to giue him thanks for all the wealth exceeding</l>
               <l>Which from his liberall hand we haue to helpe our needing:</l>
               <l>And to be ſhort, ſans ceaſe to meditate on all</l>
               <l>The countles benefites that from his goodnes fall</l>
               <l>Not ſuffering any hower to paſſe awaie for nought</l>
               <l>Without exalting him in deed or word or thought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet doth the world eſteeme this, a moſt hard eſtate</l>
               <l>And him that feeles the ſame, it counts vnfortunate,</l>
               <l>But I would gladly ſee ſome other ſtate wherein</l>
               <l>With ſuch commoditie, ſo much content is ſeen;</l>
               <l>Wherein leſſe hinderance and leſſe incomberance lies,</l>
               <l>To make men miſſe the path vnto perfections priſe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sure ſir (will ſome man ſay) you ſet a good face on-it</l>
               <l>One might at length conuert, commenting ſo vpon-it</l>
               <l>The cruellſt priſon houſe into a manſion faire,</l>
               <l>Where 'twere not hard to liue content and voide of care:</l>
               <l>You take your priſon for a practiue man of art,</l>
               <l>But ſuch as thoſe God knowes you find the feweſt part:</l>
               <l>You faine him to be frend to ſolitude and quiet</l>
               <l>But the moſt part are prone to reuell and to riot:</l>
               <l>One muſt be free from noiſe that meanes to ſtuddie well,</l>
               <l>Whereof who can be ſure in ſuch a ſeruile hell?</l>
               <l>Beſides hee muſt haue bookes, and paper pen and inke,</l>
               <l>All which in priſoners hands are ſeldom left I thinke;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:16"/>So that you do not faine your gaile ſo good and gainfull</l>
               <l>As to find out the ſame is difficulte and painfull.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I anſwear in a word (if any ſo ſhall wrangle,)</l>
               <l>I do not bound all bliſſe within ſo ſtraight an angle:</l>
               <l>I ſay great happines and hart-reuiuing ioy</l>
               <l>Followes th'aflicted ſort in euery ſharp anoy:</l>
               <l>But that there is no croſſe that doth ſo much auaile,</l>
               <l>To make vs fit to helpe our neighbour, as the gaile,</l>
               <l>Wherein the God of grace at his good pleaſure giues,</l>
               <l>Meanes to effect the ſame, vnto the leaſt that liues.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But be it ſo, in bands, that nothing learne we can,</l>
               <l>Tis to be learnd inough, to be an honeſt man:</l>
               <l>And this is th'onlie ſchole, wherin th' Arch-maiſter teacheh,</l>
               <l>Himſelfe, by ſecret meanes, rules that the rudeſt reacheth</l>
               <l>Th'aduiſe of ſuch a one more profit doth impart</l>
               <l>Then of the wicked ſort with all their curious art.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Concerning ſolitude, although that commonly</l>
               <l>Our nature be inclind vnto the contrarie;</l>
               <l>There, the asſiſtant grace of God wee cheefly find</l>
               <l>Who changing of our place doth alſo change our minde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For being free from noiſe and for obtaining tooles</l>
               <l>To helpe our knowledge with, as in all other skooles:</l>
               <l>God euer cares for thoſe that feare his name for loue.</l>
               <l>And if that any ſuch, ſuch inconuenience proue</l>
               <l>If any money need, or els through ample diſtance</l>
               <l>Be deſtitute of frends, he getts them for asſiſtance</l>
               <l>The fauour of their foes, whoſe harts he handles ſo</l>
               <l>(Howeuer they intend his childrens ouerthrow)</l>
               <l>That his, of what they need haue euermore inough,</l>
               <l>According as he knowes to be to their behoofe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now ſay that we conſent (ſay ſome) that this is true:</l>
               <l>But what if ſomwhat worſe then all this wurſt enſue?</l>
               <l>What if he be enforc't his countrey to forſake?</l>
               <l>What if continuall fitts his ſickly bodie ſhake?</l>
               <l>What if he loſe at once his wealth and reputation?</l>
               <l>Repleat on a uery ſide with euery ſharp vexacion?</l>
               <l>Can hee ſtill kepe his ioye, and can he ſtill retaine</l>
               <l>Such meanes to profit ſtill, for all this greef and paine?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Concerning his content, it's alwaies all a-like,</l>
               <l>Whether that euery greef particularly ſtrike,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:17"/>Or whether all at once he feele their vtmoſt anger,</l>
               <l>And if he be ſupriſd with ſo extreme a languor</l>
               <l>That (as I ſaid before) the ſpirit it inforce</l>
               <l>Through ſuffering of the ſmart that doth afflict the corps,</l>
               <l>To leaue his offices, ſo that he cannot wright</l>
               <l>Nor read nor meditate nor ſtudie, nor indight.</l>
               <l>It is ſo quickly paſt, that in compariſon,</l>
               <l>regarding ſo great good, tis not to thinke vpon.</l>
               <l>For, by a mightie greefe, our life is quickly ended,</l>
               <l>Or els by remedie it ſelfe is ſoone amended:</l>
               <l>And if it be but mean, then is it borne the better</l>
               <l>And ſo vnto the ſoule it is not any letter.</l>
               <l>Beſides, we muſt conceaue, our ſpirit (as oppreſt</l>
               <l>With fainting wearines,) ſometimes deſireth reſt,</l>
               <l>To gather ſtrength again, during which needfull pawſe</l>
               <l>We are not to be blamd, ſith need the ſame doth cauſe:</l>
               <l>So that the time that's loſt while ſuch ſharp pangs do paine</l>
               <l>May be ſuppoſd a time of taking breath againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In priſon (to conclude) a man at once may trie</l>
               <l>All manner of extreames of earthlie miſerie:</l>
               <l>In which reſpect perhaps the worſe ſome deeme of it,</l>
               <l>Beeing as, tweare the but that all men ſtriue to hit,</l>
               <l>But I eſteeme the ſame the perfecter for that:</l>
               <l>For if one croſſe alone can make vs eleuate</l>
               <l>Our groueling earth deſires from cogitacions baſe,</l>
               <l>To haue recourſe to God, and to implore his grace,</l>
               <l>Seeking in him alone our perfect ioye and bliſſe:</l>
               <l>Much more ſhall many greefs at once accompliſh this.</l>
               <l>For many can doe more then one (without reſpect)</l>
               <l>And ſtill, the greater cauſe, the greater the effect.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Indeed (ſay otherſome) theſe reaſons haue ſome reaſon</l>
               <l>But then whence commes it that ſo many men in priſon</l>
               <l>With hundred thouſand paines, pincht and oppreſſed ſore,</l>
               <l>In ſteed of bettering thear, wax wurſer then before,</l>
               <l>Inſteed of ſweet content, do ſtill complaine and crie,</l>
               <l>In ſteed of learning more, loſe former induſtrie?</l>
               <l>Though (in apparance great) your ſayings ſeeme but iuſt</l>
               <l>Yet plaine experience (ſure) we thinke is beſt to truſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That hidden vertue rare that ſo great good atchiues,</l>
               <l>Lies in the priſoners hart not in his heauie giues,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:17"/>The good grow better there, the bad becomme the wurſe</l>
               <l>For by their ſinne they turne Gods blesſing into curſe.</l>
               <l>And that's the cauſe the moſt are malcontent and ſad</l>
               <l>Sith euermore the good are fewer then the bad.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But wherefore doth not God to all vouchſafe this grace?</l>
               <l>Proud earth-wormes, pawſe we there: let's feare before his face,</l>
               <l>Admiring humblie all his holie iudgments high</l>
               <l>Exceeding all too farr our weake capacitie.</l>
               <l>The potters veſſell vile, doth vs our leſſon ſhow</l>
               <l>Which argues not with him why he hath made it ſo:</l>
               <l>Much leſſe may we contend, but rather reſt content</l>
               <l>With that which God hath giuen. He is omnipotent,</l>
               <l>All gratious, and all good, moſt iuſt, and perfit wiſe:</l>
               <l>On ſome, he poures a ſea of his benignities,</l>
               <l>On ſome, a ſhallow brooke, on other ſome, a floode.</l>
               <l>Giuing to ſome, a ſmale, to ſome a greater good:</l>
               <l>As, from eternitie hath pleaſd th'eternall Spirit</l>
               <l>To loue men more or leſſe, without reſpect of merrit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For my part ſhould I liue ten <hi>Neſtor's</hi> yeers to paſſe,</l>
               <l>Had I a hundred tongues more ſmooth then <hi>Tullye's</hi> was,</l>
               <l>Had I a voice of ſteele, and had I brazen ſides,</l>
               <l>And learning more then all the <hi>Helyconian</hi> guides;</l>
               <l>Yet were I all too-weake to tell the many graces</l>
               <l>That in ten thouſand ſorts, and in ten thouſand places,</l>
               <l>Ten hundred thouſand times he hath vouchſafed mee</l>
               <l>Not for my merrits ſake but for his mercie free.</l>
               <l>But yet mong all the goods that of his liberall bountie</l>
               <l>I haue receaud ſo oft, non to compare accoumpt-I</l>
               <l>With this cloſe priſonment, wherein he doth with-draw-me</l>
               <l>Far from the wanton world, and to himſelfe doth draw-me</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I poaſted on a pace to ruine and perdicion</l>
               <l>When by this ſharp-ſweet pil, my cunning kind Phiſicion</l>
               <l>Did purge (maugre my will) the poiſonie humor fell</l>
               <l>Wherwith my ſin-ſick hart alreadie gan to ſwell.</l>
               <l>I lookt for nothing leſſe then for theſe miſeries</l>
               <l>And paines that I haue prou'd, the world's vaine vanities</l>
               <l>Had ſo ſeduce't my ſoule, with baits of ſugred bane,</l>
               <l>That it was death to me from pleaſure to be tane:</l>
               <l>But, (crosſing my requeſt) God for my profit, gaue</l>
               <l>Me quight the contrarie to that which I did craue.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:18"/>So that, my body barring from a freedome ſmall,</l>
               <l>He ſet my ſoule at large, which vnto ſinne was thrall.</l>
               <l>Wounding with musket ſhot my feeble arme, he cured</l>
               <l>The feſtring ſores of ſinne, the which my ſoule endured:</l>
               <l>Tripping me from the top of ſome meane dignitie,</l>
               <l>Which drew me vp to climbe the mount of vanitie,</l>
               <l>He raiſde me from the depth of vices darkſome cell,</l>
               <l>The which inceſſantly did ding me downe to hel:</l>
               <l>Eaſing me (to conclude) of all the griefe and care,</l>
               <l>wherewith theſe falſe delights for euer ſauced are.</l>
               <l>He made me find and feele amid my moſt annoyes,</l>
               <l>A thouſand true contents, and thouſand perfect ioyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſome perhaps amaz'd, wil muſe what kinde of pleaſure</l>
               <l>Here I can take, and how I paſſe my time and leaſure:</l>
               <l>For in foule idleneſſe to ſpend ſo large a time,</l>
               <l>It cannot be denyed to be a grieuous cryme.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Firſt, in the morning, when the ſpirit is freſh and fit,</l>
               <l>I ſucke the honney ſweet from foorth the ſacred writ,</l>
               <l>Wherin by faith we taſte that true celeſtiall bread,</l>
               <l>Whence our immortall ſoules are euer only fed:</l>
               <l>Then ſearch I out the ſawes of other ſage diuines,</l>
               <l>(The beſt here to be had) among whoſe humaine lines,</l>
               <l>Supported by the grace of Gods eſpeciall power,</l>
               <l>I leaue the thorne behind, and plucke the healthſome flower.</l>
               <l>Sometimes I doe admire, in books of heathen men,</l>
               <l>Graue ſayings ſauoring more a ſacred Chriſtian pen,</l>
               <l>Than manie of our age, whoſe bold vnlearned pride,</l>
               <l>Thinking to honour God, hath errd on euery ſide:</l>
               <l>Sometimes, when I obſerue in euery ancient ſtorie,</l>
               <l>Such vertuous preſidents, trimme patternes of true glory:</l>
               <l>I wofully bewaile our wretched wicked daies,</l>
               <l>where vertue is deſpiſde, and vice hath all the praiſe.</l>
               <l>Oft I lament to ſee ſo many noble wits,</l>
               <l>(Neglecting Gods high praiſe, that beſt their learning fits)</l>
               <l>To ſing of nought but lyes, and loves &amp; wanton theames,</l>
               <l>Falſe ſooth-ſinne flatteries, and idle Fairie dreames,</l>
               <l>Then turning towards thoſe, that fild with holier flame,</l>
               <l>For onely ſubiect chooſe th'Eternals ſacred name:</l>
               <l>Theſe chiefly I admire, whoſe honourable browes</l>
               <l>Diſdayne the fayned crowne of fading <hi>Laurel</hi> boughs,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:18"/>Then full-gorg'd with the ſweets of ſuch a daintie feaſt</l>
               <l>(Prickt forward with deſire to imitate the beſt)</l>
               <l>Oft times I excerciſe this arte-les muſe of mine</l>
               <l>To ſing in holie verſe ſome argument deuine.</l>
               <l>One while to praiſe my God for all receaued good:</l>
               <l>An other while to beg, that in his deere ſonnes blood</l>
               <l>My blacke ſinnes he will waſh, and that he will not waigh</l>
               <l>At his high iuſtice beame, how I haue gon a-ſtray.</l>
               <l>Somtimes, theſe wretched times to pittie and deplore</l>
               <l>Wherein the wicked ones do floriſh more and more,</l>
               <l>Somtimes to waile the ſtate of ſad diſtreſſed <hi>Sion</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Imploring to her aide the Tribe of <hi>Iudah's</hi> Lion.</l>
               <l>If any other theame at any time I take,</l>
               <l>Yet neuer doth my verſe the ſetled bounds forſake</l>
               <l>That veritie preſcribes, nor now no more diſguiſe</l>
               <l>The vgly face of ſinne with maske of painted lies.</l>
               <l>And though that heertofore, I alſo in my time</l>
               <l>Haue writ loues vanities, in wanton idle rime:</l>
               <l>Twas as a whet-ſtone that whereon I whet my ſtile,</l>
               <l>Yer it weare ablely-apt ought grauer to compile:</l>
               <l>Yet I repent thereof: for wee muſt neuer tend</l>
               <l>To bring by euill meanes a good intent to end.</l>
               <l>When as my wearie ſpirits ſome relaxacion aske,</l>
               <l>To recreate the ſame, I take ſome other taske,</l>
               <l>One while vpon the Lute, my nimble ioints I plie,</l>
               <l>Then on the Virginalls, to whoſe ſweet harmonie</l>
               <l>Marrying my ſimple voice in ſolemne tunes I ſing</l>
               <l>Some pſalme or holy ſong, vnto the heauenly King.</l>
               <l>So that the idleſt hower of all the time that flies</l>
               <l>So faſt, is neuer free from ſome good excerciſe.</l>
               <l>Wherein I ioie as much, as euer I haue donne,</l>
               <l>In the moſt choice delights found vnderneth rhe ſunne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But you can neuer walke nor go to take the aire</l>
               <l>Nor once looke out of doore, be weather nere ſo faire,</l>
               <l>But there in ſolitud you leade your life alone</l>
               <l>Bard from the fellowſhip of almoſt euerie one,</l>
               <l>Which doubtles at the laſt muſt greeue you needs I thinke.</l>
               <l>A man that neuer thirſts hath neuer need of drincke</l>
               <l>So though I be bereft theſe other things you ſpeake-of</l>
               <l>I miſſe nor mind them not, as things I neuer reake-of.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:19"/>For I haue ſcoold my hart ſince my captiuitie,</l>
               <l>To wiſh for nothing els, but what is graunted mee</l>
               <l>And what is graunted me, contents me pasſing well.</l>
               <l>In each condition doth ſome contentment dwell:</l>
               <l>But men of differing ſtates haue difference in delights,</l>
               <l>What pleaſeth common eyes, that irketh princes ſights,</l>
               <l>What raſhelings do delight that ſober men diſpiſe,</l>
               <l>What fooles take pleaſure in, doth but offend the wiſe,</l>
               <l>What proſperous people loath, afflicted folke will loue,</l>
               <l>And what the free abhorr that priſoners will approue.</l>
               <l>But all haue equally indifferent power to make</l>
               <l>Them equally content, that can them rightly take:</l>
               <l>For who ſo preſently, himſelfe can rightly beare,</l>
               <l>Hath neither paſſed ill, nor future ill to feare:</l>
               <l>Th'one, which is now no more, ought now no more affray-vs</l>
               <l>Th'other, which is not yet, as little can diſmay-vs</l>
               <l>For what no eſſence hath, that alſo hath no might,</l>
               <l>And that which hath power, can do a man no ſpight.</l>
               <l>Beſids, ſith that our life is but a pilgrimage;</l>
               <l>Through which we dalie paſſe to th'heauenly heritage:</l>
               <l>Although it ſeeme to thee that theſe my bands do let-mee</l>
               <l>Yet haſt I to the goale the which my God hath ſet-me</l>
               <l>As faſt as thou that runſt thy ſelfe ſo out of breath</l>
               <l>In poaſting night and day, by dales and hills and heath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If thou haue open feelds, and I be priſoner</l>
               <l>T'importeth me no more, then to the mariner,</l>
               <l>Whether he go to ſea ſhipt in ſome ſpatious arke</l>
               <l>Or els at leſſer ſcope abord ſome leſſer barke.</l>
               <l>Nay, heer the leaſt is beſt, ſith this vaſt occean wide</l>
               <l>Whereon we daily ſaile a thouſand rocks doth hide</l>
               <l>Gainſt which the greater ſhips are caſt awaye full oft</l>
               <l>While ſmall boats, for the moſt, float ouer ſafe aloft.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then may I well conclude with reaſon and aſſurance</l>
               <l>That thear's no better ſtate then to be kept in durance,</l>
               <l>A ſweeter kind of life I neuer prou'd then thear:</l>
               <l>Nor was I euer toucht with leſſer greefe and care:</l>
               <l>If that I care at all it is for others cauſe</l>
               <l>And for the miſeries this times corruption drawes:</l>
               <l>But being well aſſur'd that nothing here betideth</l>
               <l>Againſt Gods ordinance and will that all things guideth</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9838:19"/>And knowing him to be good, iuſt and moſt of might</l>
               <l>I gladlie yeeld my ſelfe to th'order hee hath pight.</l>
               <l>For he it is, that now makes me accept ſo well</l>
               <l>And like of this eſtate which others hate as hell,</l>
               <l>He t'is that heretofore vouchſaft me like releefe</l>
               <l>When as I was oppreſt with a more greeuous greefe:</l>
               <l>He t'is from whom I hope in time too-come no leſſe</l>
               <l>Athough a hundred fold were dubbled my diſtreſſe.</l>
               <l>Yea hee it is that makes me profit euery day,</l>
               <l>And alſo ſo content in this eſtate to ſtay,</l>
               <l>That of my libertie I am not now ſo faine</l>
               <l>To thinke by libertie a happier life to gaine</l>
               <l>For I were well content no more from hence to go,</l>
               <l>If I might profit moſt my frends and cuntrie ſo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now here I humblie praie (expecting ſuch an end)</l>
               <l>The Lord ſtill towards me his fauour to extend,</l>
               <l>And that he will vouchſafe ſtill to alott like grace,</l>
               <l>To all that for like cauſe are handled in like caſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
